Bibliography of Jamestown Sources
National Park Service, Colonial Williamsburg Foundation, College of William and Mary
- Articles/Chapters/Papers
  - Davidson, Thomas E. "Pottery-Making in Seventeenth-Century Virginia." Dispatch: A Quarterly Newsletter of the Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation (Fall 1995): 4; illus., 543
    An overview of efforts to establish potteries in seventeenth-century Virginia.
  - ---. "Supplying the Jamestown Colony." Dispatch: A Quarterly Newsletter of the Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation (Winter 1995): 4-5; illus., 544
    An account of the efforts of the Virginia Company to keep the colonists supplied with provisions and new settlers.
  - Davis, Chris. "One More Time: A Replica of the Godspeed, the Square-Rigger That Landed at the Jamestown Colony in 1607, Proves That Crossing the Atlantic Hasn't Gotten Any Easier." Motor Boating and Sailing 157 (March 1986): 62ff.; illus., photo., chart., 545
  - Davis, Richard Beale. "The Devil in Virginia in the Seventeenth Century." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 65 (1957): 131-49., 546
    Discusses Virginians' attitudes toward the idea of black magic through the seventeenth century, including the witchcraft charges against Joan Wright which came before the General Court in Jamestown in 1626
  - A Day in Old James City: The Jamestown Exposition. National Magazine [Boston] 26, no. 2 (May 1907): 214-22; illus., 547
    A sentimental visit to Jamestown, via Williamsburg, during the tercentennial exposition. Illustrations include photographs of the church tower at Jamestown and exposition buildings in Norfolk.
  - [Descriptions of the Jamestown Tercentennial Exposition and Information on Rail Travel to the Exposition Site.] Book of the Royal Blue 10, no. 4 (1907): 22 pp. [special issue]; illus., map., 548
    Published by the Passenger Department of the Baltimore and Ohio Railroad.
  - Earle, Carville V. "Environment, Disease and Mortality in Early Virginia." Journal of Historical Geography 5 (1979): 365-90; maps, tables., 549
    Between 1607 and 1624 typhoid fever and dysentery visited Jamestown in epidemics killing thirty percent or more of the colonists with each onslaught. The Virginia Company did not understand the connection between the estuarine environment and disease. The prevention of disease and death required the abandonment of Jamestown and relocation into healthier areas, which occurred to a greater degree with the dissolution of the Virginia Company in 1624
    Includes bibliographical referencesA slightly altered version of this article appears under the same title in The Chesapeake in the Seventeenth Century: Essays on Anglo-American Society, edited by Thad W. Tate and David L. Ammerman, pp. 96-125 (Chapel Hill: University of North Carolina Press, 1979).
  - ---. "The First English Towns of North America." Geographical Review 67 (1977): 34-50; illus., tables., 550
    Offers the monopolist-migration model for interpreting the location and early growth of colonial towns. This model stresses the role of political-economic and demographic variables. Various colonial towns, including Jamestown, are analyzed and comparedIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Egloff, Nancy. "'Ancient and Chief Seats of Government': The Colonial Capitals of Virginia and Maryland." Dispatch: A Quarterly Newsletter of the Jamestown-Yorktown Foundation (Winter 1997): 4-5; illus., 551
    A comparison of Jamestown and St. Mary's City as seventeenth-century colonial capitals.
  - Fausz, J. Frederick. "An 'Abundance of Blood Shed on Both Sides': England's First Indian War, 1609-1614." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 98 (1990): 3-56; illus., tables, map., 552
    Investigates the actions and motivations of both sides.
  - Ford, Gary D. "Breaking New Ground: Jamestown Settlement, Virginia." Southern Living 29 (June 1994): 32-33; illus., photo., 553
    An exhibit of artifacts from seventeenth-century Virginia are on display at the Jamestown Settlement. Aside from newly-discovered pieces, visitors can also view archaeologists at work at the Colonial National Historical Park.
  - Forman, Henry Chandlee. "The Bygone 'Subberbs of James Cittie.'" William and Mary Quarterly, 2d ser., 20 (1940): 475-86; map., 554
    Describes Pasbyhayes, the "suburb" of Jamestown on the Governor's Land north of the isthmus. Includes a map showing the sites discussed.
  - ---. "The Old Hardware of James Towne." Antiques 39 (1941): 30-32; illus., 555
    Identifies and illustrates iron hinges, keys, locks, and other hardware recently excavated in the New Towne area.
  - Franklin, Lucy Brown. "The Negro Exhibition of the Jamestown Tercentennial Exposition of 1907." Negro History Bulletin 38 (1975): 408-13., 556
    The Negro Development and Exposition Company was chartered to organize an African-American exhibit at the Jamestown Exposition of 1607. Many black leaders opposed a separate exhibit, fearing it would foster segregation.
  - Gannon, Michael V. "Carry Me Back to Old La Florida." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 93 (1985): 79-92., 557
    Discusses the similarities and differences between Jamestown and St. Augustine, the two oldest surviving European settlements in the territory that became the United States. Although the Spanish and English differed greatly in their approaches to colonization, they shared some noteworthy similaritiesIncludes bibliographical references.
  - [Girardin, Louis Hue]. "Account of James-Town, the First English Settlement in Virginia." Amoenitates Graphicae 1 (1805): 7-10; col. plate., 558
    A brief history of Jamestown, with descriptions of the "small peninsula" and its ruins. Suggests that the nation provide an enclosure for the church tower and cemetery and a suitable monument to the foundersAn appendix describes the effects of erosion. Off the southern shore about 150-200 paces are "many yards of the palisade erected by the first settlers." On the western shore a "very narrow slip of land," which is flooded at high tide, is the only obstacle to the peninsula becoming an islandA "View of James-Town," facing page seven, is drawn from a perspective off the southwest shore. It includes the church tower, sepulchral monuments, a fence along the shore, and cattle, with two large houses in the backgroundThe article appears in the first and only issue of a magazine published by a professor at the College of William and Mary. The only known copy, with missing cover and torn pages, is held by the John D. Rockefeller Jr. Library, Colonial Williamsburg FoundationReference: Wayne Barrett, "Monsieur Girardin's Prescient Little Magazine," Colonial Williamsburg: The Journal of the Colonial Williamsburg Foundation 14, no. 2 (Winter 1991-1992): 24-28.
  - Gookin, Warner F. "The First Leaders at Jamestown." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 58 (1950): 181-93., 559
    Argues that Bartholomew Gosnold played a prominent role in the establishment of the Virginia Company and the Jamestown colony, and that John Smith exaggerated his own contributionIncludes bibliographical references.
  - ---. "Who Was Bartholomew Gosnold?" William and Mary Quarterly, 3d ser., 6 (1949): 398-415., 560
  - "Gosnold of the Godspeed." Colonial Homes 13, no. 4 (August 1987): 120-21; photos., 561
    Replicas of three ships that brought colonists to Virginia in 1607 are docked at Jamestown Festival Park: the Susan Constant, the Discovery, and the Godspeed, the latter commanded by Bartholomew Gosnold.
  - Graves, Charles Marshall. "The Pompeii of America." The New England Magazine 33 (1905): [277]-284; illus., 562
    Describes efforts by the Barneys, the APVA, the U.S. Congress, John Tyler, Jr., and Samuel Yonge to rescue, excavate, protect and preserve the ruins of Jamestown.
  - Gregory, George C. "Jamestown, First Brick State House." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 43 (1935): 193-99., 563
    Documentation relating to the first statehouse, the foundations of which were located and partially uncovered by Gregory in 1932.
  - ---. "Log Houses at Jamestown, 1607." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 44 (1936): 287-95., 564
  - Hanna, Susan D. "Preliminary Study of the Makers Marks and Dates on Lead Window Cames from Jamestown, Virginia." Paper presented at the annual meeting of the Society for Historical Archaeology, Williamsburg, 1984., 565
    The interiors of lead strips bear maker's marks and dates which can provide important information for dating a structure.
  - Hantman, Jeffrey L. "Between Powhatan and Quirank: Reconstructing Monacan Culture and History in the Context of Jamestown." American Anthropologist 92 (1990): 676-90., 566
    Primarily concerned with describing an interior Indian culture, the Monacan, a people who were less complex than, and a principal enemy of, the Powhatan. Analysis of ethnohistoric texts, and insights derived from archaeology, lead to a different perspective on the context of the Jamestown settlement.
  - ---. "Caliban's Own Voice: American Indian Views of the Other in Colonial Virginia." New Literary History 23 (Winter 1992): 69ff., 567
    The writings of William Strachey, probably a source for Shakespeare's character Caliban, described the varied reactions of Virginia Indians to Europeans at the Jamestown colony. This diversity of responses among Powhatans and Monacans contributed to the contradictions portrayed in Caliban.
  - Harrington, J. C. "Archaeology as an Auxiliary Science to American History." American Anthropologist 57, no. 6 (1955): 1121-30., 1212
    The author explains his approach to the new field of historical archaeology by referencing work at Jamestown.
  - ---. "Dating Stem Fragments of Seventeenth- and Eighteenth-Century Clay Tobacco Pipes." Archeological Society of Virginia Quarterly Bulletin 9, no. 1 (1954): 10-14., 568
    Pipe stem diameter is used as a dating tool for the first time.
  - ---. "Historic Site Archaeology in the United States." In Archaeology of the Eastern United States, edited by James B. Griffin, 335-44. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1952., 1211
    Relies heavily on Jamestown experience.
  - ---. "Interpreting Jamestown to the Visitor." The Museum News 24, no. 11 (1946): 7-8., 569
    In order to give visitors an insight into the significance of Jamestown, the author suggests not a reconstruction but a museum, where the visitor can obtain the information that will allow an appreciation of the exposed foundations and ruinsFrom a paper read at the Annual Meeting of the American Association of Museums, Washington, D.C., May 1946.
  - ---. "Jamestown Archaeology in Retrospect." In The Scope of Historical Archaeology, edited by David G. Orr and Daniel G. Crozier, 29-53. Philadelphia: Temple University, 1984., 1210
    A retrospective of archaeological projects at Jamestown, including recommendations for further work.
  - ---. "Partnership at Jamestown: Archeology and History Work Hand in Hand." The Regional Review (National Park Service) 5, no. 2/3 (1940): 2-6., 570
  - ---. "Seventeenth-Century Brickmaking and Tilemaking at Jamestown, Virginia." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 58 (1950): 16-39., 571
  - ---. "Some Delft Tiles Found at Jamestown." Antiques 59 (1951): 36-37., 572
    Short review of tiles and their decoration.
  - ---. "Tobacco Pipes from Jamestown." Archeological Society of Virginia Quarterly Bulletin 5, no. 4 (1951): 2-8., 573
  - ---. "The Tools of America's First Glass Blowers." The Chronicle of the Early American Industries Association 10 (1957): 4-5, 11; illus., 574
    Examples of glassworkers' tools were not uncovered during excavations at the Glass House site, but designs for tools to be used in the reconstructed Glass House were based on illustrations in the works of Agricola and BlancourThis article is followed by "Notes on Glass Blowing" (pp. 5-6, 11), which was extracted from Harrington's Glassmaking at Jamestown.
  - Harrington, Virginia S. "Theories and Evidence for the Location of James Fort." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 93 (1985): 36-53; map, photos., 575
    Erosion, records that conflict, and contradictory theories all affect archaeologists' ability to find the site of the fort. New anthropological research methods, satellite photography, and other studies may finally reveal the fort's original location Includes bibliographical references.
  - Hatch, Charles E., Jr. "The 'Affair near James Island' (or, 'The Battle of Green Spring'), July 6, 1781." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 53 (1945): 172-96., 576
  - ---. "Glassmaking in Virginia, 1607-1625." William and Mary Quarterly, 2d ser., 21 (1941): 119-38, 227-38; map, plates., 577
  - ---. "The Great Road: Earliest Highway Used and Developed by the English at Jamestown." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 57 (1949): 14-21; plate., 578
    Discusses the discovery of traces of a seventeenth-century road leading from the isthmus to a point near the Church. Based on excavations from 1939 through 1948
  - ---. "Jamestown and the Revolution." William and Mary Quarterly, 2d ser., 22 (1942): 30-38; plate., 579
    A brief account of Jamestown's role in the American Revolution, as taken from a report prepared by the author in 1941 for the Colonial National Historical Park, Yorktown, entitled "Preliminary Historical Study of the Lawrence and Beverley Tracts on Jamestown Island."Includes bibliographical references.
  - ---. "Mulberry Trees and Silkworms: Sericulture in Early Virginia." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 65 (1957): 3-61; illus., 580
  - ---. "Robert Sully at Jamestown, 1854." William and Mary Quarterly, 2d ser., 581
    22 (1942): 343-52; platesRobert Sully was a portrait painter in Richmond who visited Jamestown in the fall of 1854. He wrote an account of his excursion in a letter to Lyman Draper and drew sketches of the church tower, a cypress tree in the river, a brick powder magazine, the "Site of the Old Colonial Fort and Magazine," and the ruins of a residence he identified as belonging to the Champion familyIncludes bibliographical references.
  - ---. "Storehouse and Customhouse." Virginia Cavalcade 16, no. 2 (1966): 12-18; illus., 582
    An account of the career of Richard Ambler (1690-1766), Yorktown merchant and customs collector for the York River District. In 1724 he married Elizabeth Jaquelin, heiress to a large tract on Jamestown Island. The author includes a brief history of the Ambler family.
  - Hayes, Kevin J. "Defining the Ideal Colonist: Captain John Smith's Revisions from A True Relation to the Proceedings to the Third Book of the Generall Historie." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 99 (1991): 123-44; illus., 583
    The varying details among Smith's three accounts indicate that he had different intentions each time he retold the story of the Jamestown settlementIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Hecht, Arthur. "Lead Production in Virginia during the Seventeenth and Eighteenth Centuries." West Virginia History 25 (1964): 173-83., 584
    Traces lead production in Virginia from its earliest discovery near Jamestown through the colonial era.
  - Hecht, Irene W. D. "The Virginia Muster of 1624/5 as a Source for Demographic History." William and Mary Quarterly, 3d ser., 30 (1973): 65-92; tables., 585
    An analysis of the 1624/5 muster in categories such as age, geographical distribution, household size, distribution of servants, and year of arrival Includes bibliographical references.
  - Hemphill, W. Edwin. "'Hallowed Be the Place.'" Virginia Cavalcade 6, no. 4 (1957): 22-29; illus., 586
    Depictions of the Jamestown church tower.
  - ---. "'Not Born for Ourselves.'" Virginia Cavalcade 6, no. 4 (1957): 5-7; illus., 587
    Unveiling of William Couper's statue of Capt. John Smith, May 13, 1909.
  - Henry, Susan L. "Terra-Cotta Tobacco Pipes in Seventeenth-Century Maryland and Virginia: A Preliminary Study." Historical Archaeology 13 (1979): 14-37., 588
    A study of mold-made terra-cotta pipes, primarily from the St. John's site (St. Mary's City) and Jamestown. The author hypothesizes that colonists made these pipes during economic depressions, when they could not afford the more expensive pipes imported from England.
  - Henry, William Wirt. "The First Legislative Assembly in America." In Annual Report of the American Historical Association for the Year 1893, 301-16., 589
    A review of the members and acts of the first assembly in 1619.
  - Historic Highways: Virginia's Colonial Parkway. Colonial Homes 17, no. 6 (December 1991): [24]-36, 39; map, photos., 590
    The Colonial Parkway illustrates 175 years of American colonial history through reconstructed communities, historic buildings, and museums. The Parkway stretches from Jamestown Island to Yorktown.
  - Hobbs, Carl H., Dennis B. Blanton, R. A. Gammisch, and J. Broadwater. "A Marine Archaeological Reconnaissance Using Side-Scan Sonar, Jamestown Island, Virginia, USA." Journal of Coastal Research 10 (1994): 351-59., 591
    A detailed side-scan sonar survey of the shallow region immediately offshore of Jamestown Island disclosed numerous features. The major feature in the imagery was in an area thought to be a likely location of the 1607 fort. Subsequent investigations retrieved seventeenth-century artifacts but were inconclusive in better identifying the major feature as other than a series of very subtle ridges with no immediately discernible underlying structure.
  - Hoffman, Bernard G. "John Clayton's 1687 Account of the Medicinal Practices of the Virginia Indians." Ethnohistory 11 (1964): 1-40; illus., 592
    Reprints and annotates a letter (British Museum Add. Ms. 4437) written to Dr. Nehemiah Grew by John Clayton, a minister at Jamestown from 1684 to 1687.
  - Hudson, J. Paul. "The Importance of Archaeology at Jamestown, Virginia, Site of the First Successful English Settlement in the New World." The Conference on Historic Site Archaeology Papers 1 (1967): 27-32., 593
    An overview of Jamestown archaeology since 1934, stressing how archaeology has added to our knowledge of life in early Virginia.
  - ---. "Jamestown Artisans and Craftsmen." Antiques 71 (1957): 47-50., 594
  - ---. "Knight's Tombstone at Jamestown, Virginia." Antiques 91 (June 1967): 760-61; illus., 595
    Description of a tombstone in the church at Jamestown, believed to be the site of George Yeardley's burial. The tombstone at one time was ornamented with monumental brasses.
  - ---. Seventeenth-Century Glass Wine Bottles and Seals Excavated at Jamestown. [Corning, N.Y.: Corning Museum of Glass, 1961]. [40] pp.; illus., 596
    Reprinted from the Journal of Glass Studies 3 (1961): 78-117.
  - ---. "The Story of Iron at Jamestown, Virginia, Where Iron Objects Were Wrought by Englishmen Almost 350 Years Ago." The Iron Worker 20, no. 3 (1956): 2-14., 597
  - ---. This Was Green Spring: Plantation, Refuge, Prison, Statehouse. Jamestown: Jamestown Foundation, [197-?] 14 pp.; illus., 598
    Reprinted from the Iron Worker.
  - Hudson, J. Paul, and C. Malcolm Watkins. "The Earliest Known English Colonial Pottery in America." Antiques 71 (1957): 51-54., 599
  - Inside a Glasshouse. National Geographic World (November 1977): 10f., 600
  - Ives, Patricia Carter. "Giles Beecher Jackson, Director-General of the Negro Development and Exposition Company of the United States for the Jamestown Tercentennial Exposition of 1907." Negro History Bulletin 38 (December 1975): 480-83; illus., 601
    Jackson was a lawyer in Richmond who founded the Negro Development and Exposition Company for the purpose of constructing an African-American exhibit at the Jamestown Exposition in NorfolkIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Jamestown. Virginia Historical Register, and Literary Advertiser 2 (1849): 138-39., 602
    A brief description of early sites, which are "now entirely, or very nearly, submerged in the river."
  - Jamestown: Dawn of a New Era. National Parks and Conservation Magazine 50, no. 4 (April 1976): 10-12; illus., 603
    A brief review of the seventeenth-century history of Jamestown.
  - Jamestown Island in 1861. William and Mary Quarterly, 1st ser., 10 (July 1901): 38-39., 604
    Contains the text of a brief letter from Colonel E. T. D. Myers, who was the military engineer at Jamestown Island in 1861.
  - Jamestown's Time Warp. Southern Living 26 (March 1991): 16; illus., photo., 605
  - Jarvis, Michael, and Jeroen van Driel. "The Vingboons Chart of the James River, Virginia, circa 1617." William and Mary Quarterly, 3d ser., 54 (1997): 377-94; maps., 606
    Describes the "Caart vande Riuier Powhatan" by Johannes Vingboons (ENTRY 910) and speculates on its date and Vingboons' sourceThe three-house symbol on the map at Jamestown, which apparently indicates a fortification, corresponds to the location of the recent excavations of the original fortIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Johnson, Clifton. "Round about Old Jamestown." Booklovers Magazine (1904): [371]-378., 607
  - Johnson, Ludwell, III. "John Smith before Jamestown." American History Illustrated 20, no. 3 (1985): 10-15., 608
    Describes the life of Captain John Smith prior to his adventures in Virginia's Jamestown colony, as documented in Smith's 1630 book The True Travels, Adventures, and Observations of Captain John Smith in Europe, Asia, Africa and America.
  - Johnson, Robert C. "The Lotteries of the Virginia Company, 1612-1621." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 74 (1966): 259-92., 609
  - ---, ed. "Virginia in 1632." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 65 (1957): 458-66., 610
    Transcripts of three letters written in Jamestown in 1632 to officials in England. The three letters are from Governor John Harvey, from the Assembly, and from the Governor and Council.
  - Jones, Gordon W. "The First Epidemic in English America." Virginia Magazine of History and Biography 71 (1963): 3-10., 611
    Lists the causes of the epidemic and discusses why it developed at Jamestown but not at Roanoke Island.
  - Jordon, Joann, and Charles Jordon. "Historic Triangle." Travel 146, no. 1 (July 1976): 26-31; illus., 612
    Describes sites and facilities at Jamestown, Williamsburg, and Yorktown.
  - Kaufman, Ralph. "Glass Blowing, America's First Industry." Pennsylvania Folklife 29, no. 4 (1980): 25-27., 613
    The first glass blowing factory was in Jamestown in 1608. Casper Wistar in Salem, N.J., in 1739, and William Stiegel in Manheim, Pa., in 1765, established glass factories.
  - Kolb, Avery. "The Tempest." American Heritage 34, no. 3 (1983): 26-35; illus., 614
    The Sea Venture's passengers survived on Bermuda in 1609 and made it to Virginia one year later in two smaller vessels.
  - Konig, David Thomas. "'Dale's Laws' and the Non-Common Law Origins of Criminal Justice in Virginia." American Journal of Legal History 26 (1982): 354-75., 615
    Dale's Laws, promulgated between 1611 and 1618, were severe and unprecedented rules for the maintenance of discipline in Jamestown. Long considered a deviation from the common law tradition, Dale's Laws provided severe punishment for those who posed a threat to social order. Penal servitude and black slavery were logical continuationsIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Kupperman, Karen Ordahl. "Apathy and Death in Early Jamestown." Journal of American History 66 (1979): 24-40., 616
    An analogy between twentieth-century prison camps and the early Jamestown settlement demonstrates the connection between nutritional diseases and such psychological factors as fear and despair. In Jamestown a complex interaction between environmental and psychological factors produced high death ratesIncludes bibliographical references.
  - Lacefield, Susan. "Fingerprinting America." Alumni Gazette (College of William and Mary) 63, no. 2 (December 1995): 18-19; photo., 617